Guide to Frank W. Mondell Papers, 1894-1959
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Frank W. Mondell papers
1894-1959
Mondell, Frank W. (Frank Wheeler), 1860-1939.
01050
9.13 cubic ft. (23 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Frank W. Mondell was a Republican politician who served as the mayor of Newcastle, Wyoming and then in the Wyoming Legislature. The collection contains correspondence, his autobiography, photographs, speeches, newspaper clippings, printed material, and scrapbooks.
Arrangement of the Collection
Collection is arranged into 7 series.
Biography
Frank W. Mondell was born 6 November 1860 in St. Louis Missouri. He settled in Wyoming in 1887 and was a Wyoming politician, coal prospector, developer of the Cambria mines and oil property in what is now the Newcastle, Wyoming area. He took an active role in establishing the town of Newcastle and served as Newcastle's first mayor. Mondell was elected State Senator to the first and second legislatures, 1890-1893, and served as president of the Wyoming State Senate in 1893. In 1894 Mondell was elected to the U.S. House of Representatives and then defeated for re-election in 1896. After serving as assistant commissioner of the General Land Office, he was again elected to the U.S. House of Representatives in1898, a position he held until 1923. He served as Republican House Majority Leader for the 66th and 67th Congresses. After an unsuccessful candidacy for the U.S. Senate, he retired from Congress in 1923. He was appointed director of the War Finance Corporation from 1923-1925, and thereafter practiced law in Washington D.C.. He died in Washington D.C. on 6 August 1939.
Scope and Content
The Frank W. Mondell papers contain correspondence which includes references to the Teapot Dome scandal and samples of his daily correspondence (1895-1934), photographs of politicians that he knew (1903-1934), scrapboooks regarding his political career (1894-1926), newspaper clippings (1906-1959), printed material (1914-1939), and speeches given by Mondell and his wife, Ida (1911-1931). There is also his autobiography that covers the early history of the Mondell family and Mondell's activities untill the end of his Congressional career in 1923 (ca. 1935).
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by Frank W. Mondell at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
The Frank W. Mondell Papers were donated to the University of Wyoming by Mrs. Dorothy Davis in the early 1960s and by Frank W. Mondell, Jr. in 1991.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of select material from this collection are available at https://digitalcollections.uwyo.edu/luna/servlet/uwydbuwy~163~163.
Access Terms
Mondell, Ida.; United States--Congress--House.; Teapot Dome Scandal--1921-1924.; Politics--Practical--Wyoming.; Politics--Practical--United States.; Politicians--Wyoming.; Coal mines and mining--Wyoming--Weston County.; Public lands--United States.; Newcastle (Wyo.)--History.; Cambria (Wyo.)--History.; Wyoming--History--To 1889.; Wyoming--History--1890-1918.; Wyoming--History--1919-1945.; Wyoming--Politics and government.; United States--Politics and government--1865-1933.; Autobiographies.; Memorabilia.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Politicians.
Politics, Government, and Law; Politics and Politicians; Mines and Mineral Resources; Laws and Legislation; Wyoming
Container List
- Series I. Autobiography
  - Frank W. Mondell Autobiography, Volumes 1 - 4, ca. 1930s (Box 1-2)
- Series II. Correspondence
  - General, 1895-1934 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Routine (Bound Volume), 1917 (Box 2)
  - Teapot Dome Scandal, 1922-1928 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series III. Speeches
  - Speeches, 1911-1925 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Speeches, 1926-1927 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Speeches - Mrs. Mondell (Ida), 1923-1931 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series IV. Scrapbooks
  - Sub-series I. Newspaper Clipping Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbook #01, 1894 - September 1896 (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook #1a, September 1896 - February 1897 (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook #2, August 1898 - February 1900 (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook #3, January 1900 - July 1902 (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook #4, April 1901 - November 1902 (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook #5, December 1902 - June 1906 (Box 6)
    - Scrapbook #6, December 1905 - November 1907 (Box 7)
    - Scrapbook #7, January 1908 - February 1909 (Box 7)
    - Scrapbook #7a, March 1909 - May 1910 (Box 8)
    - Scrapbook #8, April 1910 - April 1911 (Box 9)
    - Scrapbook #9, January 1911 - April 1911 (Box 9)
    - Scrapbook #10, April 1911 - September 1912 (Box 10)
    - Scrapbook #11, August 1912 - June 1914 (Box 10)
    - Scrapbook #12, August 1914 - April 1915 (Box 11)
    - Scrapbook #13, April 1915 - October 1916 (Box 11)
    - Scrapbook #14, July 1916 - January 1918 (Box 12)
    - Scrapbook #15, September 1916 - April 1918 (Box 12)
    - Scrapbook #16, December 1917 - March 1919 (Box 13)
    - Scrapbook #17, March - September 1919 (Box 13)
    - Scrapbook #18a, 1922 (Box 14)
    - Scrapbook #18, August 1919 - April 1921 (Box 15)
    - Scrapbook #18b, 1923 (Box 15)
    - Scrapbook #19, July 1922 - January 1923 (Box 16)
    - Scrapbook #20, 1923-1926 (Box 17)
  - Sub-series II. Invitation Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbook 1, 1905-1912 (Box 18)
    - Scrapbook 2, 1901-1903 (Box 18)
    - Scrapbook 3, 1900-1932 (Box 19)
    - Scrapbook 4, 1921-1922 (Box 20)
    - Scrapbook 5, 1915-1916 (Box 20)
    - Scrapbook 6, 1908-1926 (Box 21)
    - Scrapbook 7, 1919-1931 (Box 22)
- Series V. Newspaper Clippings
  - Miscellaneous, 1906-1959 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Frank W. Mondell (Ida), 1931-1934 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - "My Story" (F.W. Mondell's Autobiography), July 26 - November 2, 1935 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - "My Story" (F.W. Mondell's Autobiography), November 2, 1935 - February 2, 1936 (Box 23, Folder 4)
- Series VI. Printed Material
  - Artwork, "The Homesteaders Friend" - Etching of Frank W. Mondell with a Wyoming Homesteader, undated (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Award - University of Wyoming Law Degree, 1934 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Invitations and Programs, 1914-1939 (Box 23, Folder 7)
- Series VII. Photographs
  - Photographs and Negatives, 1919-1934 (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Stereocards - President Theodore Roosevelt in Newcastle, Wyoming, 4 items (photocopies), 1903 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Stereocards - President Theodore Roosevelt in Newcastle, Wyoming, 4 items (originals), 1903 (Stereocard Box)